<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excellence of the order of the Church of England, under Episcopal government set forth in a sermon at the visitation at Blandford, Anno 1640 / by William Sherley ...</title>
            <author>Sherley, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12055869</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12055869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 823:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excellence of the order of the Church of England, under Episcopal government set forth in a sermon at the visitation at Blandford, Anno 1640 / by William Sherley ...</title>
                  <author>Sherley, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, XII, 3-4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:53145:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo: Stradling, Rev. in Chriſto, Pat. Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berto Epiſc. Lond. à Sac. Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>Ex Aed: Sabaud. <date>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Jul. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53145:1"/>
            <p>THE EXCELLENCE Of the ORDER of the Church of England, UNDER <hi>EPISCOPAL GOVERNMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth in a SERMON AT THE Viſitation at <hi>BLANDFORD, Anno</hi> 1640.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Sherley,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Tho: Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53145:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53145:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend FATHER in GOD, GEORGE, By Divine Providence, Lord Biſhop of <hi>WINCHESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis being the onely VVriting of the Author, that is found to ſurvive both him, and the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe times that oppreſt him, I am bold to make it my humble ſuit to Your Lordſhip, that for our ſecurity, leaſt after all the reſt, this Relick, which I may properly ſay, was ſaved, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould periſh alſo, You would give us leave to inſcribe Your great Name to ſo ſmall a Piece; So, as by Providence it hath eſcaped the fiery <hi>Ordael;</hi> being upheld by Your Name, no otherwiſe then the <hi>anti-diluvian</hi> Memoir's by the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of <hi>Seth,</hi> ſhall it be ſecure from any future Deluge, and tranſmitted to Poſterity as a remainder, by which they may eſteem the greatneſs of their loſs in thoſe many
<pb facs="tcp:53145:3"/>Papers both of him, and other worthy Perſons, rifled in the common Calamity. <hi>My Lord,</hi> it is the confidence we have, that had God preſerved till now the Life of our Relation, You would have accepted his Perſon, that makes me thus forward to beg Your Lordſhips Patron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to this little Orphan, that ſome are pleaſed to think is too good to periſh: nor (however unable my judgement is in matters of this moment) will my affection and near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Author, give me leave to have a leſs then the common eſtimation of it, That am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humbly devoted Servant,</hi> Ri: Harris.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Inner Temple,</hi> 
                  <date>June <hi>25. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53145:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Text, 1 Cor. c. 11. v. 34.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the reſt will I ſet in order when I come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church here on Earth, however She be the Spouſe of Chriſt, hath never yet been ſo fair, but that according to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe, inſtar Lunae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb: <hi>3.</hi> Hexaem.</note> like the Moon in the full, ſhe hath always had her Spots: Theſe being one of thoſe Notes whereby She is to be known from that Elder Siſter of Hers, triumphant in the Heavens, the Church above. Some evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence whereof may be here obſerved in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> which being planted by no meaner an hand then that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> how could it but be imagined, that the Harveſt would prove very good where there was ſuch a Seeds-man? and that few or no Weeds would have there grown up, where the Soil in its ſelf being firſt well prepared; the Grain like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe was ſo clean. But as in the Parable, ſo likewiſe here, the Husbandman had no ſooner ſown good Seed in his Field, but the Enemy came and caſt on Tares: for the rooting up whereof, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> compoſed this Epiſtle; an Epiſtle here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſo full of bitter reproofs,<note place="margin">Tertull: Li. de pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icit. c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> as that <hi>Tertullian</hi> deems it to be <hi>totam conſcriptam,</hi> written all over from the beginning to the end, <hi>non Atramento ſed Felle,</hi> not with Ink, but Gall. I liſt not now to indite anew theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> of thoſe Schiſms and Hereſies, for which my Apoſtle already hath, even in this Epiſtle, long ago, both arraigned and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53145:4"/>them alſo. That onely, what you for the preſent ought rather to take notice of, is this, That S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> having through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this whole Chapter taxed them for divers irreverent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviors of theirs in the Church; and underſtanding too withal, that for want of decent <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, many other things were amiſs amongſt them, he conceives it not ſo convenient to commit all to Ink and Paper, but reprieving the rectifying of theſe unto a farther day, he promiſeth, upon this employment, to come him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf amongſt them: for ſo far hath he been pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his minde in the Text, ſaying here to them, in theſe words which now have been read to you, <hi>The reſt will I ſet in order when I come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words then, you ſee, are the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who being now at <hi>Philippi,</hi> writes unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> That for the redreſs of ſome certain matters in their Church, which were out of order, he would, by taking a Journey thither, vouchſafe them a <hi>viſitation:</hi> So that they cannot but be conceived, to be very appoſite for that occaſion, which hath called us likewiſe at this time together: The Face in the Glaſs, anſwering not the Face that looks upon it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a more exact proportion, then theſe two ſeem to comply each with other. But that I may not be thought without method and <hi>Order,</hi> to handle a Text, the main end whereof is nothing elſe but Order, give me leave to quarter it out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you with what evenneſs I may, into juſt four parts; which too, as having a reſpect not onely to the words themſelves, but to this our meeting alſo, ſhall be no other then theſe that follow. Namely,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, The Perſon viſiting, who promiſeth here to viſit, and that is S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> intimated here in the Pronoun, <hi>I.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53145:4"/>
                  <item>Secondly, His Viſitation, expreſſed in the word, <hi>Come.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, The end of his Viſitation, <hi>To ſet in Order.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, The Object, or thoſe things that he meant to have ordered, which here lye veiled under this indefinite term, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the reſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of all theſe, and that too, according to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod that hath been propoſed; beginning with the Perſon viſiting, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe worth was ſuch, as that he may very well be thought to have deſerved ſo far, as to have even at your hands, in the firſt place, an hearing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Order,</hi> as it is conceived by <hi>Nazianzene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naz. Ora. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very Mother of Beings, and Womb of all Things: that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mentioned by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Book <hi>De Mundo;</hi> that Univerſal Soul, whereunto the World owes the benefit of its Preſervation: This being ſo eminent throughout the whole Univerſe, as that <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> from the meer Contemplation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Stob. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> chriſtned firſt the World by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Nay, ſo great an obſerver of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is God Himſelf to be acknowledged, as that <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> is pleaſed to derive the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the Greek Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. <hi>1.</hi> lib. Stro.</note> from his methodical placing and diſpoſing of all ſuch Bodies as have been created by Him: whereas, much to the ſame purpoſe alſo, it is a Note of <hi>Nazianzen</hi>'s,<note place="margin">Naz. Orat. ſup. citat.</note> in that Oration of his which but now was cited, That the Almighty, being able in Himſelf to have made all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53145:5"/>things in an inſtant, choſe nevertheleſs, to produce them one after another; ſome on the firſt day, others on the ſecond, and ſo on forward, until the ſeventh, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the end that Order might be of one and the ſame ſtanding with the World it ſelf. So that however S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath raiſed a Queſtion,<note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no, in caſe <hi>Adam</hi> had not faln, there ſhould have been a <hi>Sub</hi> and a <hi>Supra,</hi> any Subordinations at all in the Societies of Men; and ſeems likewiſe to incline to the Negative, for that the very firſt time we meet in Scripture with the word Servant (which too, according to the forecited Fathers obſervation, is in the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Gen.</hi> and the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) it being there ſpoken by way of a Curſe; he from thence collects, that <hi>Nomen iſtud Culpa Meruit, non Natura,</hi> Sin alone, and not Nature, gave a Being unto that Condition: Yet for certain, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the Fall, as matters have ſtood, without an orderly <hi>Series</hi> of Men, wherein, as in a Predicament, ſome may be <hi>Summa Genera</hi> above, others <hi>Species In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimae</hi> beneath, and a third between both, <hi>Genera ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterna,</hi> there can be no ſubſiſting for any one Society whatſoever: This being ſo neceſſary for all Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, as that without this, ſo many Men being but as ſo much confuſed Rubbiſh, or like a multitude of Stones lying in an heap together, come to be without any benefit at all each of other; whereas, being once diſpoſed of to ſuch divers uſes and ſeveral places, as they by their education have been fitted for, they then may make, not an handſome onely, but a good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable piece of Building. And if it be thus in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53145:5"/>State, then doubtleſs muſt it be more then ſo in the Church; She having ever been eſteemed an <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> whoſe Members ought, in that manner, to be ranked and ſorted into higher and lower <hi>Claſſes,</hi> as that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon upon at the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, ſhe is likened to an Army with Banners; nay, however an Army ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once diſplayed her Banners, and going on upon a March, be a great Deſciple and Servant unto Order; yet is it conceived by St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. <hi>10</hi> Hom. in <hi>1</hi> Ep. ad Theſſ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the Church in Her Diſcipline, is and ought to be more preciſe and regular, then the Field Military is in its. For hence, Beloved, came it here to paſs, that my Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> having planted now a Church in <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſuffers not thoſe <hi>Elders</hi> whom he had there ordained, to be their own <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or reciprocally, and by turn, as it were, to be Governors each to other; but knowing, that in the Church eſpecially, nothing could be more unequal then ſuch an equality, He therefore holds in his own hands the reigns of Government, he himſelf reſerves unto himſelf <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſdiction;</hi> which too, he did not onely exerciſe for that year and half a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (mentioned in the 18<hi rend="sup">h</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) that he lived amongſt them, all which time <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as the word uſed there by the Holy Ghoſt in the Orignal, is moſt obſervable) he ſate there and governed, as a Biſhop in his Cathedral; but being once removed and abſent, he grew even in this reſpect the bolder towards them: whilſt in this very Epiſtle, at the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter, and the 21 Verſe, he threatens them a whipping with his <hi>Apoſtolical Rod;</hi> at the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter, and the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53145:6"/>Verſe, he ſends out a thundring <hi>Excommunication</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Inceſtuous Perſon: at the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter, and the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Verſe, he conſtitutes <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Ordinances;</hi> whereas at the ſixteenth Chapter, and the firſt Verſe, he enacts a ſpecial <hi>Edict</hi> for the obſervation of them. Nay, finally that it might appear, that he was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any one particular that might declare him to be their Biſhop, he acquaints them here in the Text, that for the Ordering of all ſuch matters, as in that Church of theirs were yet out of Order, he himſelf would come and <hi>viſit</hi> them; and who is there but will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that without all contradiction, <hi>the leſs ever hath</hi> thus <hi>been viſited by the greater?</hi> So that if we lay all together, and adde to this his viſiting here, thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Epiſcopal Acts</hi> of his, but now ſpoken off, which he did otherwhere; and then, however that illiterate, ignorant Scotchman (for before ſo Learned an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as this,<note place="margin">Scoti <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Paracleſis contra Pan. Tileni Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeneſin.</note> to whom now I ſpeak, the Author, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then ſo; is not worth a naming) hath in a jeer, as ſilly altogether as himſelf, been pleaſed to ſnear it out, that <hi>Profecto Paulus fuit Peſsimus Dominus Epiſcopus, Verily Paul was but an ill Lord Biſhop,</hi> yet will it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by appear, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (for however the Man, for fear of Idolatry, dur'ſt not beſtow the Saint on the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, yet Religion hath taught us better manners then not to do it) that I ſay, even Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, did in his Authority <hi>Lord</hi> it as much, as any of thoſe our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelates; whom he, out of the depth of his ignorance, can by no means fancy.</p>
            <p>Neither ought it to be conceived as a Marvel, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53145:6"/>my Apoſtle, ſo early now at the firſt, erects this kinde of <hi>Church-Government</hi> amongſt the <hi>Clergy</hi> here at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth;</hi> ſince as if this were in a manner natural and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to her, the Church ſeldom or never hath anciently been obſerved to have ſtood without it. Thus in the old Teſtament we finde, that amongſt the Jews, there were not onely <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> but an <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> alſo, who was even then ſo lively an Emblem of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as that hereupon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Summus Sacerdos,</hi> have ſince familiarly been uſed, in the Writings of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, no otherwiſe then as <hi>Synonoma</hi>'s with the word <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</hi> Whereas in the New it is to be read, that our bleſſed Savior, whom <hi>Ignatius</hi> is not afraid to call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">Ignat. Ep. ad Magneſ. Tertull. l. <hi>4.</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Mar. c. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> and after him too <hi>Tertullian, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticum Dei Patris Pontificem,</hi> all other Biſhops being, as it ſhould ſeem, but <hi>Copies</hi> onely taken from him; like one of that Order <hi>licenceth</hi> the <hi>Twelve,</hi> together with the <hi>Seventy,</hi> to Preach the Goſpel; until at laſt, immediately before his aſcenſion, lifting up his hands and bleſſing the Apoſtles, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.51.<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>97.</hi> quaeſt. de Novo Teſt.</note> 
               <hi>Per iſtam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum impoſitionem</hi> (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſeems to believe) <hi>Apoſtolos ordinavit Epiſcopos: By that laying of his hands upon the Apoſtles, he ordained them to be Biſhops.</hi> Sure I am, that Antiquity thought it no prejudice at all to the Apoſtles to have this Opinion of them, and therefore,<note place="margin">Theodoret. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi> Baſil. Cyprian: Ep. <hi>65.</hi> Hierom: ad Marcellum.</note> as the Greek Fathers were wont to call Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal Government, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: So likewiſe, who knows not but that it is as uſual with the Latine to ſtile the Apoſtles themſelves, in plain terms, Biſhops; as having no meaner authority
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53145:7"/>for this, then that of St. <hi>Peters</hi> own example, who in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.20. ſpeaking of <hi>Judas</hi> his Apoſtleſhip, calls it there by no other name, then by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>his Biſhoprick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> lived in theſe Renowned Worthies, yet may we not imagine, that it died like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with their Perſons; whil'ſt they, like thoſe that ran in the <hi>Olympian</hi> Games, delivered that Light into the Hands of Poſterity, which ſuch as went before had put in their's. Hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> ordained <hi>Timothy Biſhop of Epheſus,</hi> and (as there is good record to be ſhewn for it) <hi>Titus</hi> of <hi>Crete;</hi> both which, even by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Commiſſion, exerciſed that meaſure of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> in each of thoſe their <hi>Dioceſſes,</hi> as that it may be made to appear, that the Reverend <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church, do, at this day, own no farther a degree of Authority, then that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in thoſe his Epiſtles afforded them.</p>
            <p>Neither went this Fire out in later Ages, which at the firſt was ſo well kindled: inſomuch that as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſpeaks it of himſelf,<note place="margin">Irenaeus, l. <hi>3.</hi> contra Val. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Habemus annumer are cos qui ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolis inſtituti ſunt Epiſcopi, &amp; ſucceſſores corum uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad nos: That he was able, for his own particular, to give a Catalogue of thoſe Biſhops, that from the Apoſtles times had ſate before him in the See of Lyons:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſhan. <hi>66</hi> Haereſ. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeh. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6</hi> &amp; <hi>11.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> c <hi>9.</hi> l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi> l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> So likewiſe <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius,</hi> taking in hand this Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, have deduced from the Apoſtles, until the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Nice,</hi> a Succeſſion of <hi>Prelacy</hi> in all the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Churches in the World, that then were extant. Whil'ſt Modern Chronologiſts, having brought down
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53145:7"/>the Line near unto this preſent Century, have hereby given unto the Pens of ſucceeding times, the occaſion of going on with that Story, which God, out of his mercy unto his Church, will, I doubt not, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue unto the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>And ſhall this Sacred Order thus now be queſtioned, which having in all Ages hitherto, ſo fair Evidences to ſhew for its Title, hath ever yet been thought to be out of queſtion? Shall the <hi>Rochet</hi> it ſelf be yet at laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed for a <hi>Rag</hi> of <hi>Popery?</hi> and for this very Reaſon, be thrown off by thoſe very Arms themſelves <hi>that once did wear it?</hi> How unhappy may we deem our ſelves, that ſo unworthy an Act as this, hath been reſerved for the diſgrace of theſe days of Ours. Whil'ſt it may be ſaid of thoſe, that have committed this infamous kinde of <hi>Church Murther</hi> upon themſelves,<note place="margin">Iſidor. l. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> what <hi>Iſidor</hi> once ſpake of a certain diſſolute Church-Man, one <hi>Zozimus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>Theſe two alone have herein done enough, to draw a ſcandal upon all the whole Clergy of the Chriſtian World.</hi> But it is impoſſible to ſpeak ſo loud, as to reach their ears whom this concerns: and therefore I turn from them, and addreſs my ſelf unto you, my Brethren, to whom I cannot but ſignifie, and that too in ſome ſuch manner, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> once beſpake his <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians,</hi> telling them, as he at leaſt ſays himſelf of a matter weeping; that when I look into Ancienter Times, and read in <hi>Peluſiot,</hi> that the People,<note place="margin">Iſidor. l. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>490.</hi>
               </note> as often as they met in the Streets with the Sacred Robe, were wont ever, in all humble manner, for to cry out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53145:8"/>(it ſounds well I am ſure in Greek, but knowing not how it would take with ſome of our Mother wits in Engliſh, I therefore ſpare the Tranſlation) when I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that they reverenced the <hi>Ephod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſidor. l. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>136.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the ſame Author, as one that did bear the Image and Place of Chriſt; and afterwards caſt mine eyes upon this our Age, wherein many think they have Religion enough, <hi>if they can but hate a Biſhop, and abhor a Ceremony;</hi> how can I then but even from thence collect, that theſe our days are the very dregs of time, and that the World, running now as it doth ſtark naught, is come to its Lees? But however ſuch ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low heads as theſe eſteem of our Reverend Prelates, no otherwiſe then as of a gay uſeleſs Pageant, ſerving meerly for Pomp and Glory; yet deeper Judgements know how to demonſtrate plainly, that the Church her ſelf is not able to ſtand without theſe Pillars: I, for mine own particular, ſhould be very jealous of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of mine <hi>Orders,</hi> had I not known my ſelf to have received them from the hands of ſome one Reverend <hi>Paul</hi> or other. Whatſoever thoſe Tranſmarine Sons of the Presbyterial Board, may think of themſelves, yet were they to be tryed at the Bar of Antiquity, they would ſcarce be found to be of the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levy.</hi> St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> who, being but a private <hi>Prieſt</hi> at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and diſcontented therefore with the meanneſs of his own Condition, grew hereupon, amongſt all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the onely Man that ſpake hardly, at leaſt if not evil, of <hi>Dignities,</hi> doth nevertheleſs in that Epiſtle of his unto <hi>Evagrius,</hi> where he pleads moſt for the honor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53145:8"/>of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> appropriate the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Ordination,</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and altogether to a <hi>Biſhop</hi> onely: <hi>Quid facit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom: Ep: ad Evag.</note> ſaith he, <hi>exceptâ ordinatione Epiſcopus, quod non facit Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter?</hi> as conceiving this to be an act utterly beyond the Sphere of a <hi>Prieſts</hi> performance.</p>
            <p>Whereas in after-ages; a Biſhop being on a time for to Ordain, and being enforced, by reaſon of a pain which he himſelf had in his Eyes, to ſuffer his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to read the Words of Conſecration,<note place="margin">Binius, tom. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>559.</hi>
               </note> the ſecond <hi>Hiſpaline Councel,</hi> that was held then at <hi>Sivil,</hi> thought it requiſite to ſit on thoſe Perſons who had been thus Ordained; who finding a <hi>Nullity</hi> in their <hi>Orders,</hi> by reaſon the Words of Conſecration were not uttered by the Biſhop himſelf, in the fifth <hi>Canon</hi> of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, adjudg'd them for no <hi>Clergy men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whither am I now gone, or whither have I been carried, being called abroad by my Text, and theſe Times together? Whil'ſt the Perſon Viſiting, having had by this his allotted Minutes, if not more then comes to his ſhare, to ſpeak for himſelf, It will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us now to haſten him to his Viſitation, which too, being at hand in my next Particular, comes now in the ſecond place, and that too in the Word, <hi>Come,</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to be treated of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si Judicas cognoſce,</hi> Knowledge ought ever to be the Uſher, the Needle as it were,<note place="margin">Seneca Trag.</note> that is to make way for the Threed of Juſtice: Whil'ſt he that ſhall adventure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the executing of the later of theſe, without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inſtructions firſt in the former, may well be liken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thoſe Prepoſterous Governors, which <hi>Munſter</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53145:9"/>makes relation of,<note place="margin">Munſter, Coſmogra: cap. de Hungar.</note> who in an <hi>Hyſteron-Proteron</hi> Cuſtom that they had, as Barbarous altogether as themſelves, were wont, upon a ſuſpition, to condemn the Party whom they conceived to be a Malefactor, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to try the Carcaſs. And therefore that my Apoſtle, being now as an Eccleſiaſtical Judge to ſit upon the ſtate of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> might the better have ſufficient informations of thoſe things, that he was there to Order, he intends to make his own Eyes their over-ſeers; whil'ſt for that purpoſe he here doth promiſe, by way of Viſitation, to come himſelf firſt amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Neither may we imagine that my Apoſtle came to write ſo well as he did without a Copy, as having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good precedents, which directed him to this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular courſe of proceeding, which here he took. Thus in that very firſt <hi>Viſitation</hi> which ever was held, for the ſetting in Order again our firſt Parents, after that irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity of their's which they had committed, <hi>Venit Omnipotent,</hi> the Almighty Himſelf comes in Perſon to view the Delinquents; <hi>For they heard the voice of the Lord walking in the Garden,</hi> Gen. 3.8. Nay, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this All knowing Viſitor, by reaſon of his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, might juſtly have ſentenced them without a Tryal; yet before he proceeds ſo far as the Act of Excommunication, for the expelling them out of a Paradice, he vouchſafes, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> very well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. <hi>17</hi> Hom. in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>To ask queſtions, receive their anſwers, and then again to queſtion them farther:</hi> And why all this? but onely to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53145:9"/>teach ſuch as ſit at the Stern of the Church this Leſſon, That they draw not ſuddenly the Spiritual Sword upon every trifle: But as often as there is juſt occaſion given to unſheath it, that they forget not the Words of the fore-cited Father, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. loc. ſuprae citat.</note>, to uſe much deliberation, and have themſelves an inward ſeeling of heart before they ſtrike; as being at ſuch times for to conſider, that even in this very act, they cut off a Limb from the Body of that Church whereof they themſelves are Members.</p>
            <p>I liſt not to mention the Lords ordering of <hi>Cain</hi> for the Blood of his Brother <hi>Abel;</hi> the doom that he paſſed on <hi>Sodom;</hi> the puniſhment wherewith he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded <hi>Babel:</hi> Though in all theſe God had his <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit,</hi> and his <hi>Viſitavit</hi> alſo, for he went down to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their defaults were anſwerable to that Cry that came up unto Him. Having onely begun with the firſt Viſitation which the Lord ever held, I ſhall end my Obſervation with that laſt Viſitation which He intends to make; that general one I mean, when <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for ſo 'tis ſtiled by St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet. c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> as in the day of an <hi>Epiſcopal Viſitation,</hi> both quick and dead ſhall be ſummoned to appear before his <hi>Conſiſtory.</hi> And though I dare not, with the boldneſs of the School-men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve on the <hi>Ubi,</hi> or the place <hi>where</hi> the Lord ſhall then ſit and Viſit, and therefore cannot direct you to what particular part of the World, that great Viſitor of Heaven and Earth ſhall then bend His Progreſs; yet that the Lord, even then, ſhall have his <hi>Venit,</hi> a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming likewiſe, you have the Authority of an Apoſtle
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53145:10"/>for it;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ. c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> the Lord himſelf, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, and with the Trump of God; the Saints ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of their Grave to meet Him in the Air, ſhall welcome Him, as thoſe Ancients did their Prelates coming into their Cities, with Acclamations and Shoots of Joy; an Arch-angel ſhall be His Voice, His Cryer, and Heaven it ſelf ſhall ſound that ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning Trump, more powerfully then that Bell, which ere while for this purpoſe you all heard rung, to call you together.</p>
            <p>And ſince that God Himſelf hath had His Comings, His Viſitations, no marvel that the Church of God, in imitation hereof, hath had Hers; whereby She en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to heal thoſe Breaches, which that great Compaſſer of Sea and Land,<note place="margin">Latimer.</note> the Devil (<hi>quo non habet Anglia Epiſcopum diligentiorem,</hi> as old Father <hi>Latimer</hi> was pleaſed once to expreſs it) in thoſe his Viſitations likewiſe inflicts upon her. A practice of that Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as that even in the Old Teſtament may you finde ſome plain foot-ſteps of it: thus <hi>Eliah,</hi> you read at the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> and the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Chapter, went from <hi>Bethel</hi> to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> from <hi>Gilgal</hi> to <hi>Jericho,</hi> and from that to <hi>Jordan,</hi> viſiting the Children of the Prophets in all thoſe places; which doing too, immediately before his being taken up to Heaven, He ſeems to intimate by the very time it ſelf wherein He did it, that the Act was Divine and Heavenly, which He left till then to be performed. Neither ſtood <hi>Eliah</hi> in this Point a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, whil'ſt in this one particular undertaking of his,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53145:10"/>the later Prophets ſucceeded him, no leſs then they did in his office; and therefore at the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Zachary,</hi> and the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, are they, as it is at leaſt in the Hebrew, ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Walkers. Whereas in the New Teſtament it ſaid of our Savior, that Great Biſhop of our Souls (for ſo is he called in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.) that he <hi>viſited</hi> us from on High, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.78. nay, that he went about all the Villages and Cities of the <hi>Jews,</hi> teaching in their <hi>Synagogues</hi> the Goſpel of the Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.35. upon which place the Note of St. <hi>Hierom</hi> is,<note place="margin">Hierom. Comment. in <hi>9.</hi> c. Mat.</note> 
               <hi>Quod aequaliter vicis &amp; urbibus &amp; magnis, &amp; parvis praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit,</hi> That our Saviour <hi>preach'd equally the Goſpel to the villages and cities, both to the great and the ſmall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: Non conſiderans Nobilium Potentiam, ſed ſalutem Credentium, Not conſidering or having reſpect to the Power of the Noble, but to the Salvation of Believers.</hi> And where the Maſter of the Houſe was ſuch, it may be well imagined that his Servants, the Apoſtles, would endeavor to ſhew themſelves like unto him; who were in this Point ſo active, as that their Life ſeem'd little elſe but a kinde of a continued Viſitation, and the whole World but one great <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> which they travelled over.<note place="margin">Iſidor. Pel. l. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>251.</hi>
               </note> The time would fail, ſhould I tell you with what expedition thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (for ſo are the Apoſtles ſtiled by <hi>Iſidor</hi>) thoſe winged Husband-men did flie from this place to that, from one Nation to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Country, ſcattering the Seeds of Diſcipline in divers Regions; planting ſome Churches, confirming others, reforming a third, and viſiting all. That Book which is written of their Acts, is full of no one thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53145:11"/>more then of this Act of theirs. Amongſt whom nevertheleſs, we may not, but in an eſpecial manner, make a particular Remembrance of this my Apoſtle here in the Text St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who having by his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. the <hi>care</hi> of all the <hi>Churches,</hi> with ſo an indefatigable an endeavor went from each to other, as that he appeared hereupon unto St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. <hi>34</hi> Hom. in Gen.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a kinde of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body, no-body, a body without a body, an Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Man. The Sun it ſelf ſeems hardly to go a larger Circuit, then that which he, viſiting, as his manner was, the Brethren, went over: Read but this <hi>Itinerary,</hi> as it is drawn out partly by St. <hi>Luke,</hi> in the 20. and 21. Chapters of the <hi>Acts;</hi> and partly by himſelf, in the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and verſe 9. and you will then acknowledge, that there may a large Map be made of his Journals onely.</p>
            <p>But the Church being all this while without enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, lay hitherto nothing elſe but as ſo much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: and therefore that it might appear how this ſo Ancient an Order went not out, when once diſtinction of Dioceſſes was brought in; look but upon thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> whom the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, in the ſecond Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> hath been pleaſed ſo far as to take notice of: The Biſhops of which ſeveral Churches, as it is Interpreted by a Learned Commentator,<note place="margin">Mendoz. <hi>in 1</hi> Sam. <hi>2.</hi> Tom. p <hi>523</hi>
               </note> are therefore there called <hi>Angels,</hi> that ſo being put in minde of their Office by their Name, they might be ready, no otherwiſe then as thoſe Miniſtring Spirits the Angels, to go hither and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53145:11"/>thither for the better ordering of that particular <hi>Dioceſs</hi> which they were to govern.</p>
            <p>And where the Wheel had ſo many good Hands to ſtir it at the firſt, how can it be expected otherwiſe then that it would keep long a going; which too it did in after Ages with that force and vigor, as that for the better keeping of it up, even beyond an uſual height, The Church thought it meet to create a new kinde of Order of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, who being by their Office to go about, and ever and anon for to viſit thoſe little Vilages that it ſtood not with the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Epiſcopal Robe, to come to himſelf, were therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Circuiters:</hi> whoſe name, as I firſt finde mentioned by <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> ſo likewiſe is the reaſon why they were firſt ordained, ſet down by the Fathers of the <hi>Laodicean Councel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Epiſc. &amp; Cleric. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Zonaras Concil.</note> in the 57 <hi>Canon</hi> thereof: whereas <hi>Zonarus,</hi> in his Expoſitions of that very <hi>Canon,</hi> explaining both their place and their name together, ſignifies that they were therefore ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, for the keeping the Church in Order, they went continually round the Country, having in no particular place any ſetled Manſion.</p>
            <p>But ſince the Heavens themſelves which now rejoyce as a Gyant to run their courſe, ſhall yet, at the laſt, wax old, as doth a Garment, how could it but be imagined that this motion likewiſe ſhould in time begin for to languiſh? The decay whereof, divers Councels taking notice of, endeavored by their Canons and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to put new life into it; as knowing, that the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53145:12"/>Church in Her Diſcipline and Doctrine both, would ſoon feel a Winter, ſhould not thoſe Lights of Hers, like that great Light above, the Sun, come yearly, by the Beams of their Authority, at a nearer diſtance then at other times to ſhine upon Her: which Councels, if you deſire to know what they were,<note place="margin">Vid. Bin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Concil. Hic citat.</note> are <hi>Concilium To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letanum quartum. Canone</hi> 35<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Concilium Bracarenſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum. Canone</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Concilium Aralatenſe. Canone</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. with divers others, whom I am not ambitious here to quote. The Edicts of all which Councels, being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into the Body of the Canon Law by <hi>Gratian,</hi> have grown hereby to be of that Authority,<note place="margin">Gratian. C. <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> C. placuit.</note> even in this our Church, as that the Year it ſelf is not more conſtant in the return of her Yearly Seaſons, then this our Church in Her as Yearly Viſitations.</p>
            <p>Thus have I, you ſee, Beloved, from the example here of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and from this his coming, which my Text makes mention of, preſented you with the Story of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Viſitations:</hi> which ſince, for many Ages together, they have been much obſerved, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, without infinite prejudice to the Wiſdom of the Church, be conceived, but that there may divers weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſons be given for them.</p>
            <p>And indeed who knows not, how the Ear of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may eaſily be abuſed in her Informations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch Particulars as lye remote, diſtant from her?<note place="margin">Tertull. Apol. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> ſince that all Allegations paſſing <hi>per Aurium &amp; Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarum Traduces</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> phraſeth it) through the hear-ſay of divers Tongues and Ears; like Waters running through Mines of a ſeveral nature, looſe uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53145:12"/>their own genuine reliſh, changing their taſte now for the better, and now again for the worſe, by having a ſtrong tang ever of that Man's diſpoſition who at the laſt hand relates them. Hence, when the cry of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> Tranſgreſſion travelled ſo far as from Earth to Heaven, the Lord ſeems not, at that diſtance, to give credit to it, but reſolves to go down and ſee, and then to judge her, <hi>Geneſis</hi> the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and the 21. in imitation of which Example,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>13.</hi> in Gen.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> preſumes to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel thoſe that have the Authority either of Church or Commonwealth put into their hands, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not to account every crying information that rides Poſt unto them, ſufficient Evidence whereon for to paſs a Sentence; but at ſome certain appointed Seaſon for to go themſelves, that ſo thoſe Fallacies, which diſtance otherwiſe might impoſe upon them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus prevented, Falſhoods may not then dare to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before them.</p>
            <p>And as Authority, were it not for theſe Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, might in ſome Particulars hear too much; ſo likewiſe in other-ſome might it hear too little: whil'ſt divers defects of the Church, here and there abroad, come hereby alone oftentimes to be known: Even as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> at the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> going through the Streets of <hi>Athens,</hi> obſerved thereby ſome ſuch Superſtitious Cuſtom, which had he not been there himſelf, might for ever, happily, lain undiſcovered. For albeit ſome, like <hi>Hermogenes</hi> in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> think it <hi>officium bonae Conſcientiae,</hi> the part of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be blabbing ever all that ill which they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53145:13"/>know of any; yet to be an Informer, is ſomewhat in it ſelf an odious Office: from which too, ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are ſo averſe, as that many a Church-warden (the more the pitty) giving up an <hi>Omnia benè,</hi> when as indeed an <hi>Omnia Peſsime</hi> had been of the two the truer, hath been known at ſuch Meetings as theſe, to have choſen to be guilty, rather of Perjury it ſelf, then in this Particular to diſcharge his Oath and Duty. Whence the Ear of Government, by reaſon of theſe blank Preſentments, can never hope to have ſo exact Intelligence as is needful for her; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how requiſite is it that the Eye of Government, like His at the firſt of the <hi>Revelation</hi> and the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, <hi>walking in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks,</hi> ſhould endeavor, in part, to be its own Informer: Whil'ſt ſhe might by theſe means obſerve here, the Houſe, even of God Himſelf, in this or that part ſo ruinous; as that were it but an Houſe for a Man to dwell in, it would ſcarce be thought Tenantable; and there a Church-man, as little going, as living ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the gravity of that Holy Profeſſion which he hath undertaken. In one place, the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of this our Mother all diſ-uſed,; and in another, the <hi>Canons</hi> themſelves made no otherwiſe then a dead Letter, to be of no force or power. In this Congregation, that moſt Heavenly piece of Devotion, the <hi>Litany,</hi> for many Years ſince baniſhed as <hi>Apocryphal;</hi> and the reſt of Divine Service ſo curtailed, upon every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and like the Garments of <hi>Davids</hi> Servants, ſo cut off at the waſt, as if the Prayers of the Church
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53145:13"/>were of little other uſe then to ſerve onely, as Muſick before a Play, to entertain the Company till the Seats be full: Whereas it may ſo fall out, that in the very next Pariſh, a Sermon on the contrary hath been ſuch Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as that the People, unleſs it be upon ſome great Solemn Feaſt or other, have not had that Diſh ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up unto them. Thus, thus may he that travels over a County, obſerve here and there the noyſom Smells, the Boggs, and the Myre of it, whereas by viewing of it at a diſtance, or in a Map, he ſhall ſee onely the Towns and the Woods, the Rivers and the Hills, nothing but what is fair in it ſelf, and a Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure likewiſe to the Eye for to behold. How ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar therefore a deſign of this was Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy altogether of ſuch an Apoſtle as He for to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take: who, the better to finiſh that Reformation which he had begun, concludes upon a Coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his <hi>Corinthians;</hi> that ſo, as for thoſe matters which in that Church of theirs were not as yet redreſſed, he might by this his <hi>Viſitation</hi> put likewiſe in <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as being the end of my Apoſtles Coming or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, and therefore in the next place now to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Will I put in Order:</hi> The Word in the Original is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies <hi>Ordinabo, Conſtituam, Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribam;</hi> ſo that my Apoſtle here in this place, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Judgement of the beſt Commentators, aims wholly at ſuch things onely as belong unto outward <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> or as St.<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>1.</hi> Ep ad Januar.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> is pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it, <hi>ad Ordinem Agendi,</hi> to the Ordering of all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53145:14"/>ſuch Services, as in the Church were to be performed. A matter, it ſhould ſeem, of no ſmall conſequence, in regard my Apoſtle beats ſo often and ſo much upon it: who having here ſpent no leſs then a whole Chapter upon this one Buſineſs, falls nevertheleſs upon it again in as ample a manner, as here he doth in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of this very ſelf-ſame Epiſtle: where, having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted likewiſe upon the Ordering of divers other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars in the Church, his concluſion there at the laſt is this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in Order,</hi> ver. 40. Nay, that he might the better mould his Son <hi>Titus</hi> to this his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in Church-affairs, he lays his Commands upon him, in the firſt Chapter of that Epiſtle, and the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, to <hi>Order the things that were wanting</hi> in the Church of <hi>Creet,</hi> ſuch it ſeems as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf had not diſpoſed of at his being there.</p>
            <p>And no marvel neither that my Apoſtle both here and other where, in himſelf and others, ſeemed ſo zealous for Order: The Church being, as anciently ſhe hath been ſtiled,<note place="margin">Conſtit. A. poſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The very School of good Order,</hi> wherein Leſſons of Order are daily to be taught, and learned, and practiced alſo: Nay, Order hath heretofore been conceived ſo proper unto the Church, as that by this, no otherwiſe then as by ſome peculiar badge or cogniſance, She anciently hath been known. No ſooner had <hi>Jacob,</hi> in that Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his, beheld the Orderly aſcending and deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Angels from Heaven, together with the Lord Himſelf, ſtanding at the top of that Ladder
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53145:14"/>whereon they went; but being once awaked from this his ſeeing of ſo much Order, he preſently makes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf this peremptory Concluſion: <hi>This is no other then the Houſe of God,</hi> Gen. 28.17. Whereas our Saviour, out of the great deſire he had to ſee no irregularity at all in the Temple, vouchſafed oftentimes to heal the Blinde, the Dumb, the Deaf and the Lame, even in the Temple; as if it had been ſo great an eye-ſoar to Him, that any in that place eſpecially, ſhould want ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Eye to read, or an Ear to hear, or a Tongue to ſpeak, or a Knee to bow, when the Diſcipline of the Church required theſe Duties of them, as that he choſe rather to be at the expenſe of a Miracle Himſelf for their redreſs. And were our Saviour yet ſtill on Earth, as indeed He is now in Heaven, how many ſuch Cures as theſe might He meet with in moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations? Some being blinde, by reaſon of a <hi>Cataract</hi> of wilful Ignorance that is grown over their eyes; others lame, in regard of a ſtrong <hi>Convulſion,</hi> which Rebellion and Inconformity have cauſed in their Knees; whereas a certain prejudice againſt the Liturgy of the Church hath ſo far poſſeſſed a third, as that this alone to them is a <hi>dumb and a deaf Spirit</hi> alſo, making them oftentimes to have the uſe neither of Tongue nor Ear in theſe our Aſſemblies: The Fancies of whoſe <hi>Humors,</hi> were they but once fed and cheriſhed, the Church would ſoon leave of to be what at the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, She is ſtiled, <hi>A Garden encloſed:</hi> A Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den being ordinarily a place of ſo exact contrivance, as that here may be obſerved a Knot, there a Square; next
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53145:15"/>to that a Bank; and above that again a Walk, hem'd in with Trees that ſtand in a row, at an equal diſtance each from other; all things being done there by line and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; diſpoſed of to the beſt advantage by method &amp; Order: whil'ſt the Church would be then a Wilderneſs, or a Foreſt rather, where without any diſtinction at all, a Lilly, a Thorn, a Bryar, Straw-berries and Thiſtles, good and bad might be ſeen to grow all upon one piece of Turf together: inſomuch that <hi>Babel</hi> it ſelf, no nor the Primitive <hi>Chaos</hi> neither, were never guilty of a greater Confuſion then that which would be then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for to be in Her.</p>
            <p>But the Text ſpeaking as here it doth, not of Order ſimply, but of putting in Order, may not but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to look equally two ways at once; whil'ſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it doth not onely point at the Neceſſity of Orders in a Church, but it reflects likewiſe upon their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in whoſe hands it lies to enact theſe Orders: ſo that as from the one ſide it is to be gathered, that there is no ſubſiſting for a Church without the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Order, in regard that Ceremonial Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, being abſolutely neceſſary for the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of all outward Acts whatever, without rules gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and obſerved concerning times, places, manner, and the like, there can be no outward Worſhip done unto God: So likewiſe from the other is it to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that every one is not Maſter of the Mint ſo far, as to preſume to ſtamp this Coyn; this being a Prerogative wherein they are to be ſharers onely, to whom the Government of the Church belongs: which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53145:15"/>is the reaſon that here in the Text, it is not one (<hi>I</hi>) that comes, and another <hi>(I)</hi> that puts in Order; but it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame <hi>(I)</hi> in both, it's the ſame numerical St. <hi>Paul</hi> that divides himſelf between both theſe acts.</p>
            <p>And indeed, many are the Orders which we finde St. <hi>Paul</hi> to have made for the Meridian of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> divers whereof are to be read in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Verſes of this preſent Chapter: all which he enacted to make uſe of a diſtinction which he himſelf ſo much harps on in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of this Epiſtle) <hi>not by commandment, and as from the Lord, but by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, and as from himſelf,</hi> giving herein his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as one that had obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful. Wherein, that I may not be thought to have delivered any private Opinion of mine own, know that you have all this warranted unto you under the hands of the deſervedly Honored Angel of the Church of <hi>Sarum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Davenant, de Jud: Controv: cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apoſtoli</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quatenus erant ordinarii Eccleſiae Rectores de hiſce ritibus externis pro ſuâ ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ ſtatuebant, quod ad adificationem Eccleſiae facere vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur:</hi> The Apoſtles, as they were ordinary Governors of the Church, preſcribed, as concerning outward Rites, ſuch things which they in their Wiſdom thought to make moſt for Edification; which Words are in that incomparable Work of his, <hi>De Judice Controver ſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Rat.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>.</p>
            <p>So that my Text being thus opened, affords us in this place ſuch a parcel of Divine Truth as this, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That the Authority of making Orders, whereby to govern each particular Church, is a Prerogative,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53145:16"/>which thoſe that ſit at the Stern thereof may rightly challenge: St. <hi>Paul,</hi> you ſee, after an ordinary way did it here in the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> and therefore thoſe that are his Succeſſors in the like condition, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully aſſume to themſelves the like employment. A Doctrine of that Evidence and Conſequence both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as that this Church of ours, in thoſe few Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Hers which She hath publiſhed, hath thought it in Her Wiſdom meet,<note place="margin">See the Book of the 39 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</note> to avouch it no leſs then twice in two ſeveral Articles, <hi>Article</hi> the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and the 34<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Nay, before ever that Book of Hers ſaw light, thoſe great Reformers, under King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as much, which too, was done with that meaſure of zeal,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> in his Book of Acts and Mon.</note> as that Biſhop <hi>Bonner</hi> was enjoyned, by the Kings Councel, to Preach at <hi>Pauls-Croſs</hi> this Doctrine; my Authority for both theſe, is <hi>Fox</hi> in his <hi>Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Edvardiſexti.</hi> Neither hath it been given to Men of this Climat onely to be of this Opinion, ſince thoſe Reformed Churches that have been beyond the Seas, have herein yielded unto us the right Hand of Fellowſhip. Witneſs the <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of the Reformed Church of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t haec confeſſio a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, lib. opuſcul.</note> publiſhed in the Year, 1562. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur</hi> (ſaith She) <hi>tum omnes, tum ſingulas Eccleſias hoc jus habere, ut leges &amp; ſtatuta ſibi condant ad Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am communem inter ſuos ſtatuendam:</hi> Witneſs likewiſe the conſent of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Divines, ſet down in that <hi>Auſpurge Confeſsion,</hi> whereof <hi>Melancton</hi> was the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver; whoſe words, much to the ſame purpoſe, are <hi>Licet Epiſcopis &amp; Paſtoribus Canones conſtituere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſourg. Coufeſſ. art. ult.</note> 
               <hi>ut ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula in Eccleſia ſiant ſecundum Ordinem.</hi> Nay, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53145:16"/>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> however conceived by ſome, to be none ſo the greateſt Friends which the Church ever had, ſtickles nevertheleſs ſo earneſtly for this, in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his Inſtitutions and the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter, as that thoſe who ſhall caſt an eye one what he there hath written, cannot but judge him to be very zealous for it.</p>
            <p>Niether ought it to be conceived, that theſe Sons of the Church in honour of their Mother, have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured herein to flatter her into a greater Priviledge, then that which by right belongs to her. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Baſil. lib. de Spiritu. quinto cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> is an ancient diſtinction made heretofore by St <hi>Baſil,</hi> Predications and matters of Faith are one thing, and Placits or matters of Order another. (For ſo is the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there, as I conceive to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, the word Ceremony being not of ſo ancient a ſtanding in the Church, as to be found in the writings either of the Greek or of the Latine Fathers. St <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> in his Retractations,<note place="margin">Austin. l. <hi>2.</hi> Ret. c. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> makes in his owne behalf an Apologie, for that it once dropp'd unawares from his Pen.) And however the Church of Rome dare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her Commiſſion ſo far, as in reſpect of the former of theſe, to make new Creeds, (for ſo Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth did;) and to blot out one of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Decalogue, for that it gain-ſayes thoſe Images which they are reſolved to ſet up and worſhip, <hi>Nos vero talem non habemus Conſuetudinem,</hi> we have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Church of God; we cannot find in our hearts for to be ſo cruell, as for the ſatiſfying of our owne cauſeleſſe Fancies, to mangle thus the body of Religion, which our Fore-fathers to the leaſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53145:17"/>Tittle therof, have even with the loſſe of their owne blood preſerved entire. All the Power which we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to our ſelves, is only about the outward dreſs and attire of the Churh, in cauſing that to be ſuitable always to her Condition: This being a liberty which in all ages hath ſo far been Challenged, as that a great part of that apparell it ſelf, wherewith the Apoſtles thought fit to cloath Her, within a Century or two, grew to be caſt off and antiquated; inſomuch that the Holy Kiſſe, the Feaſts of Charity, Abſtinence from things ſtrangled, the imploying of Widdows in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Services, with the like (however Orders all of the Apoſtles owne Compoſing,) in ſome ſhort time came for to be difuſed. Wheras we read likewiſe of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Ludo. Viv. in Aug. de Civit. dei l. <hi>6.</hi> c: <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> that in his owne Church at <hi>Millaine,</hi> abrogated an old Order which they had of Feaſting at the Tombes of the Martyrs; in regard the People in his time made it an occaſion to draw on drunkenneſſe. Nay, however <hi>Trina Merſio,</hi> the threefold dipping in the Sacrament of Baptiſme, was at the firſt eſtabliſhed upon no meaner a Ground, then for ſignification of the Three Perſons in the Bleſſed Trinity, yet by reaſon the <hi>Arians</hi> took the advantage thereof to countenance their Hereſie,<note place="margin">Binius. Con. cil. Tolet. Can. <hi>5<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi>
               </note> the Fourth <hi>Toletan</hi> Councell blotted that Order out of the Rubrick. And why may not the Church ſtill be Miſtreſs of ſo much Power as to do the like, as long as thoſe Sonnes of Heirs, who are ſet for to rule, are engaged in the Action: whereas, if every Private Member ſhould be ſuffered to have therin a Finger, how might we then in time look to have as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53145:17"/>many Editions of Service-books, as there is of Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacks, every year a new one? as alſo, there would be then, here in the Temple, as much Variety of Geſture as there is of Faces, whil'ſt one diſliking this Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, another that, a third queſtioning all, nothing of Order would be then agreed on.<note place="margin">Bernard lib. de interi: domo.</note> St. <hi>Bernard</hi> notes it of the People in his days, that whereas the Lord (in the twelf Chapter of <hi>Exodus</hi>) commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in token of their deliverance out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to kill a Lambe, and to ſprinckle the blood thereof on the door poſts with a Branch of Hyſſop, and after that (in the fifteenth Chapter of Numbers) enjoyned them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make Fringes in the borders of their Garments, to mind them hereby of his Commandements, and to put upon the Fringes, a Ribband of Blew ſilke; They grew ſo bold as to aske, why the Remembrance of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> deliverance was to be done by the blood rather of a Lambe, then of a Goate, or a Calfe, or a Bullock, or of Turtle doves, and why with a Branch of Hyſſop, rather then with Roſe mary; as alſo, why the minding of Gods Commandements was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed rather by Fringes then by Laces, in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Garment rather then in the mid'ſt, with blew Ribbands rather then yellow or green; Thus were the People there ſo great over-weeners of their owne Particular private Fancies, as that hereupon they proceeded ſo far, as to queſtion the Lords owne Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. How much more would they pick a quarrel at each others Orders, were they but once admitted unto ſuch compoſures? it being uſual with Perſons of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53145:18"/>that Quality, who have not been beholding to Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſo much judgment, as might ſerve them to correct their Fancies; to think no Muſick ſo good, as that which they make themſelves, and to conceive their own Children, though never ſo ill-favoured, to be nevertheleſs very fair.</p>
            <p>And here, Beloved, we have all great reaſon to bleſs the Lord God of Heaven, for that he hath been pleaſed to be ſo Favourable to this Chuch of Ours, as ever ſince the Reformation, to continue to her ſuch Nurſing Fathers, who have in that manner Ordered all Things, as that for Doctrine and Diſcipline both, ſhe may now be very well conceived to be the wonder of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World. For to ſay nothing of the Former of theſe, and the unparalel'd Purity thereof, in regard my Text gives me not here any hint to reflect on that, how hath her Diſcipline been in that manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, as that whereas there are required,<note place="margin">Calvin l. <hi>4.</hi> inſt. c. <hi>10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> even by <hi>Cal. vin</hi> himſelf, in Church Rites but three Conditions; namely, <hi>In Numero Paucitas, in Obſervatione Facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, in ſignificatione Dignitas;</hi> theſe Three are all ſo Eminent in our Rites and Ceremonies, as if none but <hi>Calvin</hi> had been at the firſt, the Compoſer of them? For however, there are many great Clouds of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in uſe with the Church of Rome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> in nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas.</note> a Number of thoſe are by us at this day diſpell'd; So that now there ſeemes to be left no greater Quantities of leaves, then may be thought requiſite to preſerve the Fruit. Whil'ſt our Church her Orders likewiſe are of that eaſie Performance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatione Facilitas.</note> as being ſuch as concerne our knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53145:18"/>at this part of the Leiturgy, our ſtanding at that, our Hearing now, then our Singing of an Hymne, with the like; as that I know not how Eaſe her ſelf could poſſibly wiſh for a more favourable imployment. And as for ſignification,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> in fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificationc dignitas.</note> ſhe is in that moſt remarkable, whil'ſt there is not ſcarce any one Rite or Order of Hers, but is a kind of viſible Sermon, putting us in mind of ſome one good leſſon or other, as often as we are to uſe it; inſomuch that they who will not be brought to hearken to what we teach, by looking on what we doe in ſuch places as theſe, may in a manner read what we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <p>Neither is this Church of ours ſo farre indebted, as ſome think ſhe is, to the Sea of Rome, for many of thoſe Ceremonies that fill her Rubrick; ſince that however they have been, it may be, in uſe with the Romiſh Faction, yet being the Rites of ancienter Primitive times, why may not we by a Right of our Owne, lay as good claime to them, as thoſe Sonnes of the <hi>Papacy</hi> have done before us? they I confeſſe, by faſtning their foule hands firſt upon them, have ſullied and ſoyled them greatly; which Pollution nevertheleſſe of theirs, we by freeing them from that abuſe which they have put upon them, have waſhed off: whereas, ſhould our Primitive Reformers for this reaſon only quite have caſhiered them, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed might have ſeem'd <hi>Curatio,</hi> a Cure to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>ſed Curatio Carnificis non Medici,</hi> as ſaith that great Oracle of Wiſdome <hi>Caſſander</hi> excellently,<note place="margin">Caſſand. Conſult.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53145:19"/>
               <hi>But the cure of an Hang-man not of a Phyſitian,</hi> not of one that deſtroys only the diſeas, and keeps the man alive that had it, but of one that makes a rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of both theſe at a clap together.</p>
            <p>No Marvail then, all things being ſo ordered with us as they are, that ev'n ſtrangers and Forrainers have been ſo farre taken with the heauty of this our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as that they, like ſo many Voluntaries have preſſed their own Pennes to doe Her Service by way of defence;<note place="margin">Bucer lib. de Refor: Eccleſ. Pet. Mart. cp. ad Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum. Caluin cp. <hi>200.</hi>
               </note> Such as have been <hi>Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> and <hi>Calvir,</hi> who as they were Men of Renown and famous all in their Generations, ſo likewiſe have they in their ſeveral writings fought againſt ſuch as have oppoſ'd Her Diſcipline: nay, a certain French Embaſſadour, one Marqueſs <hi>Rogncy,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our late Kings reigne, of bleſſed Memory; veiwing of our Church Orders, firſt at the Cathedral in Canterbury, and then at his Majeſties Chappel royall at Court, ſaid hereupon, that if the reformed Churches in France had kept the ſame Order as we have done, he was aſſured there would have been in that Country many thouſands more Proteſtants then now there are:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Barlow Conf. Hampt. Court. p. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> which Paſſage I ſhould not peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (in this place that now I here ſtand before you in) have taken notice off, had not his Reverend Pen who compiled the ſtory of the Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> thought it meet for to have publiſhed it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World.</p>
            <p>But alas, how hath this our Mother, who hath been admired thus by ſtrangers, been deſpiſed nevertheleſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53145:19"/>by Her owne Children? ſo that it will be an hard matter to ſay, whether Her happineſs in the One, or Unhappineſs in the other, be of the two the greater: whil'ſt ſome unnaturall Sonnes of Her owne, ſuckled by Her in Her Boſome have traduced Her ſo farre, as to call Her Church-Muſick Meretricious,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See T. C.</hi> apud <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whitgift.</hi> The view of the Popiſh abuſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main. <hi>1. Oxford</hi> Anſwer to the humble Petition.</note> Her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſals and Readings of the Pſalms <hi>alternatim,</hi> the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing of Tennis-balls; her Collects becauſe but briefe, Cuts and Shreds of Prayer; her Choice of Epiſtles and Goſpels, the mangling of the word of God; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that neither the Hymne of Glory, the Creed, the Nicene I mean, and that of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> no, nor the Lords Prayer it ſelf, have eſcaped them without a moſt bitter cenſure; all which ſeem to me, at leaſt for to be ſo ſtrange, as that common Charity would not have ſuffered me to have believed the leaſt Tittle thereof, were not all this and more to be read in their own Books and Writings. Nay, becauſe our Temples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin now to appear ſomewhat like, what they are, the Houſes of God, wherein the Lord ought to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in the beauty of Holineſs; becauſe our Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries have of late been entred with that lowlie Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as becomes the Courts of the moſt High; how hath this our Virgin Mother been lately ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized, as if ſhe were turning Harlot, in going a whoring after Popiſh Vanities? But what Credit do theſe ſilly Libellers do in the mean time to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> in calling that Popery, which the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienter Purer times will not be aſhamed to own as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53145:20"/>theirs; amongſt whom, as there is mention made of Churches that have been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Cyril. <hi>14.</hi> Catech.</note> ſo adorned and even emboſſed with Silver and Gold, as that they ſeemed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>10.</hi> lib.</note> a kind of wonder to as many as beheld them: So likewiſe is there to be read (in the <hi>Jus Orientale</hi>) of ſome ſuch thing as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Nay in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> of a <hi>Terram Fronte concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientes,</hi> men not entring then the Church, as ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily now many do, with that geſture and countenance, as if they went thither, rather with authority to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſſeſs God of his Houſe, then to humble themſelves before him; whilſt in the words of the Pſalmiſt rather, <hi>they then came and worſhipped, and fell down and knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before the Lord their Maker:</hi> And therefore what ſhall I ſay to theſe, or how may I hope to move them? Shall I endeavour to unbend their ſtiff ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits by gentle Perſuaſions and loving exhortations? but preſuming that ſuch Phyſick will be too weak to move their tuffe Tempers, I may not but think of ſome ſuch ſtrong Doſes as that, which I meet with in the Writings of an <hi>Italian</hi> Prelate, who hath a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that where God comes, and ſees his Houſe for to ly neglected,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Frederic Borrom. <hi>Synodal.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>even in that duſt that he finds there, he writes the ſinns of thoſe, by whoſe default it was kept no better:</hi> And what the Finger of the Lord once writes, be it but in duſt, is to be conceived to be as durable, as if it were engraven with the pen of a Diamond in a Pillar of Marble. And thus hahing now declared unto you at large, the end of my Apoſtles coming or Viſitation, which was, for to put in Order, and withall, taken the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53145:20"/>occaſion of diſcharging that duty in mine own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,<note place="margin">Can. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> which the <hi>Canons</hi> of our late Holy Synod hath laid on us, in ſhewing the laudibleneſs of the Orders and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> It remaines that we now proceed to thoſe Things, which my Apoſtle meant for to put in Order; and they as I told you are here veild up in this Indefinite Terme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Reſt, <hi>The Reſt will I ſet in Order, when I come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What thoſe, Reſt, Things were, which my Apoſtle intended at his coming amongſt the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for to have Ordered, I find neither here nor otherwhere expreſſed; ſo that Commentators by reaſon of this my Apoſtles ſilence, having but a cold ſent to hunt by, are generally all of them at a Loſs: ſome running this way, and ſome that, as their own private Fancies, and ſuch conjectures as they make to themſelves, ſhall ſeem to lead them. Seeing therefore it is ſomewhat dangerous, there to ſet up Sails for a further Journy, where neither Sun nor Star appears for our Guidance, and whereto we have no certain Card of our own to ſteer by; I hold it the ſafeſt courſe here to caſt mine Ankor, ſhutting up all in one Word only of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which alſo ſhall be no other then that which this very point it ſelf may be made to yeeld us; whilſt this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Reſt,</hi> however it be indefinite in it ſelf may ſerve, nevertheleſs to Teach you all your duties.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then as for you the Wardens, who being,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lindwood</hi> Conſtit. l. <hi>3.</hi> de Cler. non Reſid.</note> as you are told by <hi>Lindwood, Eccleſiae Occonomi,</hi> the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53145:21"/>Churches Oeconomiſts, that are by your Place, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for Her Wants; nay, who have been conceived to be ſo far the Hand of the Biſhop for the putting his Mandats in Execution,<note place="margin">Concil. Gangr. C. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; C. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> as that in ſome of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Councels you are ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the men em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by him, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Men ordered by him, let this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> heer in the Text be your Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer ſo far as to cauſe you to Preſent all thoſe things, which you in your ſeveral Churches know yet ſtill to be out of Order. Which that you may not think to be meerly a Freewil buſineſs, or a matter at pleaſure only, know, that in caſe you do it not, by Vertue of the Oath which for this purpoſe hath been taken by you, you are guiltie of Perjury, and ſo (for that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive will work moſt with you) liable to the heavy Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of higher Courts.</p>
            <p>And as for you, Much Honoured (for as Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors upon good grounds conceive S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> went not himſelf, as he here reſolved, to <hi>Corinth</hi>) who are in the place of our Reverend <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> and now come to order ſuch grievances as ſhall be made known to you, if there have been with you a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Nos qui vobis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demur lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui de ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periori loco, ſub p dibus veſtris ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi>
               </note> any ſuch things I mean, which in thoſe bills as have been preferr'd, you have not taken ſufficient notice of, he that here ſtands on high, caſts himſelf ſo low as your feet, for to beſeech you that admitting ſuch things into your further thoughts, you would be pleaſed to ſend out your edicts for their Reformation.</p>
            <p>But as for you, My brethren, ſince you at your very firſt entrie into the miniſterie, all took Orders, and are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53145:21"/>therefore now all men of Orders: There is nothing I hope with ſuch as you, that is out of Order; but if there be, let this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here in the Text have ſo much influence likewiſe on you, as to cauſe you to be your own Ordinaries ſo far, as by amending in your own Perſons what is amiſſe, to put all that in Order. Thus ſhall theſe our yeerly Meetings be freed from thoſe Jeers and Scoffs, which ſome envious Tongues have been ready to caſt upon them; whileſt theſe our Viſitations then ſhall be to the Reforming of every one of us in Particular, to the Honour of the Church in general; and finally to the Glory of God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Holy Ghoſt; to which Bleſſed Trinitie in Unitie, and Unitie in Trinitie be aſcribed all Majeſty and Worſhip, both now and eyermore. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
